in this video I want to introduce you to
a simple method for professional it
troubleshooting I call it the Oda method
now what's a professional a professional
is somebody who uses an approach that is
shared by other professionals it's
shared and because of that it is
reliable it is more consistent and it is
above all more
scalable amateurs do it on their own way
they're individuals they do It For the
Love of it that's what the word amateur
means for the
loving they can be faster or better than
professionals maybe maybe not but the
bottom line is alone you go faster
together you go further that's what
professionals do go
together step one observe or in D
raming what do you see that you don't
expect or what do you expect that you
don't don't see here's an example this
is what we see this however is what we
expect it's not the same
thing the result of this step is a
description of the situation that can be
replayed or at least reviewed by
somebody
else and a test you can do or an
exercise you can do is write something
down and then give it to somebody else
to see if they actually can understand
it and can move to the next
step you want to record all of these
steps in what I call your Oda log this
is your bread Chum Trail you
meticulously log every action and every
result as it
happens maybe even before it happens you
want to prefix those with a capital O in
the text
file and you want to copy and paste and
and Link whatever it is that you observe
from uh the systems that you're working
with at the beginning of the log at the
start you will title your problem you
also explain your objective what it is
that you're trying to reach what is your
definition of done so to say your first
author name and starting date of this
process you also want to have a section
A tldr that you will update with the
progress um whenever you take a break
I'll talk about that in a moment
it is really convenient to turn this to
have this on a shared file like Ms teams
or Google drive or uh whatever it is
that works for you you really want
somebody else um to uh to give them a
chance to help you that's what being a
professional is all
about the next step is hypothesize or in
Dutch
foring you want to research the possible
causes of the observation what caused
what you see an example could be uh
based on your own model of how it should
work and I'll talk about that in the
next slide you could also Google or
stack Overflow or an error message if
you're completely cluess like everybody
does you can refer back to your own
earlier Oda LS that have a similar
problem you can ask somebody but in any
case you want to document your Search
keywords and possibly also the Google or
stack over flow links that look the most
promising the result of this is a
credible idea a believable idea of what
might actually cause that observation
and again somebody else should be able
to understand that
reasoning and more than one idea is
actually better now hypothesizing might
involve doing additional experiments
that may not solve the problem but that
will give us new observations as input
put to the whole
story let's have a look at how we can
create a hypothesis that are based on
how we think it should work so on the
top right again we're not connected to
the internet and our mental model is
something like okay we're not connected
my phone is not is connected to the
Wi-Fi the Wi-Fi is connected to the home
router the home router is connected to
the
internet each of these things could be
broken so those are then three
hypothesis my phone is not connected
next question how do you test for that
uh that will be a diagnostic or a
setting on your phone you have a look at
your phone it does the phone think it is
connected and you can make up your um
own approaches to testing any of the
other
hypothesis let's get into an example uh
different example the Linux uh we're
typing more read me and we're getting
another message permission denied
now that's an observation right it's
very likely not what we want to see so
we can hypothesize what's going on here
what could possibly be wrong and we can
think about what will give us a little
bit more information on that uh
situation on that observation I'll get
back to this example in a
moment step three we decide on a couple
of courses of action write down the best
actions that you can think of in the
your Odo log and before you actually do
them good actions are hypothesis driven
they are um easy to execute um they have
quick
turnaround uh they are
informative and most of all they are
potentially
successful now sometimes or most of the
times actually this involves a trade-off
because things that are easy to execute
don't necessarily give us a lot of
information and things that are really
informative could take a long time to do
so this is where the art still comes in
the result of this step is a couple of
these actions Again replayable by
somebody else somebody else could
actually do them and if we're into a
really large scale troubleshooting
activity we might actually parcel these
actions out to different teams to to
figure
out in summary that course of action
every course of action should either
solve the problem or give us more
relevant
information step four the final one act
do and
Dutch we take our best shot and we
document it we make it traceable and
replayable for example in a software
development environment or maybe in a
gith UPS environment we record a
specific git commit ID so that we know
what we did so we can play it back we
can we figure that out that's what
version control is about you also want
to record the results of the step before
you proceed um move into the loop again
the result of this is an executed
intervention something that you've
actually done and that leads us to a new
observation and as I said you include
the details that a competent person
needs to replay
this we want to use use uh uh the OD
loog in every
step if there's a URL you copy it in
there if there's a screenshot that you
can take that's relevant put it in there
you want to copy paste command lines in
fact my suggestion my habit as a matter
of fact is to type the command line into
my Oda log paste it into the system
rather than the other way around that
makes it more reproducible if it was
wrong I just copy that thing again I
copy that thing and fix it and and try
again you also want to include any
rabbit hole that you took for a couple
of
reasons uh it's a warning for somebody
else kids don't try this at
home but it might not be a rabbit hole
after all or maybe when you have a
slightly different approach there is
some value in
there you also want to proceed all the
lines that you have with an O of an o or
an H or a d or an A appro as appropriate
to the
situation you might also want to
consider a different style or color for
computer output uh to distinguish
between actual observations and stuff
that you've typed in from somewhere else
you also want to name your documents in
a consistent way so you can retrieve
them later the log and the date and the
topic are the most important
things back to a small example our
observation is permission denied now
thinking this through as a Unix expert
we might go like okay hypothesis one the
file has the wrong permissions another
hypothesis is we may not be the user
that we think we are what is a course of
action that checks the first hypothesis
well uh that will be easy that would be
LS minus L although there's probably a
couple of other ways uh of doing
this and then as a result uh we see that
the file has permissions 0 0 0 which
basically means that you can't do
anything with it and that explains the
observation we know how to fix this or
we can derive ways of fixing this that's
another uh iteration in the
loop at every Oda log uh once we've made
some progress we want to have a tldr
paragraph at the top it summarizes the
problem it summarizes the status of
where we are and if there's a solution
we give uh the the gist of it for
anybody interested in more details
they'll dive into the document and I
tell you these documents can become
long you also once you're done you have
solved the problem or you decided it's a
100% dead end you want to create a
lesson learned out of that document you
want to clean it up by doing two things
one is to cross out any dead ends not
don't delete them cross them out you
want to show that you took the path and
it actually didn't work that's valid and
important information you also want to
make it more self-contained because
typically you forget to put in things
that after a couple of weeks you go like
what was that
again so the big idea uh of the Oda
method is uh by executing specific
technical interventions we achieve
desired and planned results and we do
that by being conscious of what are our
desired results what are our technical
uh act options make them explicit be
explicit about our planned actions and
as a result bu we can achieve more
reliable performance as well as work
with and teach other
people I know this reflection takes
practice uh being a
professional is a process not a state of
mind in summary the OD Loop starts with
observe then we hypothesize what could
cause that observation we decide what we
want to do to change the situation or
actually
um execute that
Intervention which will lead us through
to new observations once we have an
observation that we're happy with we can
stop otherwise we'll go through the loop
a couple of times and again practice
makes perfect because you still derail
every now and
then I hope this was helpful um like And
subscribe uh good luck with your
troubleshooting and thanks for watching